We're looking at loops we've looked at for loops we've looked at while loops.
But we want to illustrate the difference between a four and a while, because they can appear to be
the same.
As we said, a for loop goes from one number to another number in a range, and it's predefined and
preset, whereas a while loop can look like it's doing the same thing, it's going to continue until
a certain condition is true.
So it can emulate a for loop.
But it is also very useful because you can use it to make a loop.
Continue until something happens when you don't know how long it's going to take.
So it's not going to be a set number of iterations.
It could be anything from zero, one to or 1000 iterations until some condition is true.
So we'll see that happen.
In this example.
What we are going to be looking at in this example is, is going to be a list of what is in your makeup
bag.
Now this could vary from person to person.
So this program is going to do is it's going to ask the user what is in your makeup bag.
Then the user is going to type it in okay I have some mascara and then click enter.
And again it's going to ask you again what is in your makeup bag.
And the user is going to keep on typing in what is in their makeup bag until they have nothing left.
And obviously it depends, you know, because my makeup bag has got like nothing in it, whereas someone
else's makeup bag may have a whole lot more items in it.
So that's why this is a great example of using the while loop, because we actually don't know how many
items are in your makeup bag.
It's up to you until a certain condition is found to be true, in which case we're going to use the
word done to indicate that I'm done with what's in the makeup bag.
So let's see how that is going to look.
So we're going to write our while we're going to use the variable r while R.
And we want to say is not equal to.
If you remember that's how we write.
Not equal to the word done or a string called done.
Okay.
Like we said before, this is going to keep on going until the user types in done.
And we're going to show you how that works.
So remember again we have to define this variable R or the or or the program is going to not know what
we're talking about.
So in this case R is actually a string and specifically R is an empty string.
So this is what I've typed here is just an empty string, which is basically a quotation with nothing
in the middle and a quotation mark.
So that is empty string.
You've set this variable to equal to that empty string.
And we want this loop to keep on going until I is equal to done.
Or in other words, while I is not equal to done.
So what did we say.
We wanted to ask the user.
Well we want to ask them what is in your makeup bag.
So hopefully you also remember how to do input.
We're going to put input and ask the user that question what is in your makeup bag.
And now also we are going to have to store this input somewhere.
So what this input actually is this input becomes R.
So each time the loop runs and the users asked this question and they type something in over here.
Whatever they type is going to be stored in R.
So for now we are just going to then print R.
So you can see exactly how this works.
Okay.
And you'll notice I don't have one of those conditions that I had last time where iterated or changed
this variable.
And that's because I'm not saying wow R is greater than done, which doesn't actually make any sense
at all.
I'm just saying keep on going until R is equal to done, or while R is not equal to done.
So let's run this.
Okay.
So let's start what is in my makeup bag let's say mascara.
Enter.
Okay.
So you see here it says mascara.
That's because over here I said print whatever R is.
So in this first one R is mascara.
But now it's still asking me.
You can notice I is a string so it's replacing it each time.
It's not going to keep mascara.
So Sarah now types the next item that's in her makeup bag of lipstick.
As it prints it, it's going to say lipstick.
It's not going to say mascara and lipstick because I is a variable can only hold one value.
This is not a list.
It's a simple string variable.
And so it's being replaced each time she enters a new item and it's printing it out.
So eyeshadow is also now added to the list.
And so as you can see this is going to continue going around and around allowing her to enter the long
list of items that are in that makeup bag.
And for some of you I said this could go on for weeks and months as you enter all sorts of things.
Well, you know what these things are, but there we go until finally you are exhausted.
And so what do we do now?
Okay, so I'm done.
That's all.
That's that's all that's in my makeup bag.
And I'm going to tap done.
And it's done.
So you'll see I'm no longer getting the question.
It's now seen okay over here as soon as I tap done or over here as soon as I tap done.
That became the variable.
Ah it came around the loop.
Is this variable I equal to done.
Yes it is.
So it said is ah not equal to.
And they said oh no, actually is equal to Dan.
So it jumped out of the loop.
So the second we tap done here, the loop ended and we we didn't have an infinite loop.
Obviously I could have carried on tapping and stuff over here forever without tapping done.
And it would be almost an infinite loop.
But I think eventually everyone would get a bit tired and you'll have to eventually tap that done.
So you can keep on doing this and keep on tapping things for as long as you want.
And as long as you don't tap done, it's going to keep on asking you that question.
So you see, this is a great example of where the while loop is very powerful and it's different to
our for loop, and it's used all the time.
I mean, you often prompted to answer things and it says tap exit when you're complete.
That's exactly what is happening.
The code behind that is basically a while loop.
So those are while loops, very powerful.
When you are not sure exactly of how many times you need to iterate.
Just one more thing.
If you remember, strings are very finicky.
So if I actually tap done.
But let's say I put a capital D, it wouldn't see it as being the same as that done over here.
So you have to tap exactly what is there for it to finish.
So let me actually show you that.
Okay.
I'm just going to have a very small makeup bag this time.
Let's just say I have mascara.
Let's say I have some bronzer.
Okay.
And now I'm done.
So let's say I want to be grammatically correct and put a capital there.
You'll see it's said, oh no, that's done in your makeup bag basically.
Okay.
So as soon as it sees this done here it goes.
Now we are done.
And it again takes us out of that loop.
So that was while loops with a bit more interesting example.
We will keep on building on to all of these things and showing you more and more complex examples and
more interesting and exciting examples.
But for now, that is what you need to know.
Obviously, change the change the question.
Try it with different stuff, try it with numbers, and then change this over here to being a number,
a number data type instead of a string.
But just play around and we'll see you in the next lesson.